A Guide to the Carl F. Emswiller, Jr. papers, 1961-2003
Virginia Commonwealth University
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Carl F. Emswiller, Jr. papers, 1961-2003
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
2011.Feb.02
4.19 linear feet.
Emswiller, Carl F., Jr., 1935-2009
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Jewell M. Emswiller of Leesburg, Virginia in 2011.
Biographical Information
Carl F. Emswiller, Jr. was born in Washington, D.C. on October 21, 1935. He served in the U.S. Navy from 1953 to October 1957 as Aviation Storekeeper, First Class. Emswiller went on to attend the Medical College of Virginia, School of Pharmacy. He graduated with a B.S. in 1962. That same year he joined Eugene V. White at his ground breaking, office-based pharmacy in Berryville, Virginia, as an associate pharmacist. During this time he and White created one of the nation's first pharmaceutical care centers. This was a very innovative idea which eschewed the traditional pharmacy model in favor of a more patient focused pharmacy.
In 1968, Emswiller purchased Edwards Drug Store in Leesburg, Virginia, where her continued to hone the patient-focused model. He moved his pharmacy in 1974 to a medical office building co-located with physicians and other health professionals. The office-based model eliminated the sale of commercial goods and was equipped with a private consulting room. Patient care services expanded to include patient medication record reviews as well as blood pressure, glucose, and cholesterol monitoring in collaboration with local physicians. This model of pharmacy service raised the pharmacist to the level of health care partner rather than simply a medication dispenser. Both White's and Emswiller's pharmacies served as examples for other pharmacists throughout the county.
Emswiller was actively engaged with his profession as a member of various professional groups including the Northern Virginia Society of Pharmacists, the Virginia Pharmaceutical Association (currently known as the Virginia Pharmacists Association), the American Pharmaceutical Association (APhA, now known as the American Pharmacists Association), the American College of Apothecaries (ACA), the American Society of Hospital Pharmacists, the American Society of Consultant Pharmacists, the American Association of the Colleges of Pharmacy, and the National Association of Retail Druggist. He held numerous positions over the years in these groups such as the chair of the ACA, member of the APhA Board of Directors, and president of the Northern Virginia Society of Pharmacists, to name a few. Emswiller also served as an associate clinical instructor of Pharmacy at Virginia Commonwealth University, MCV campus for more than 25 years and also served as the chair of the Virginia State Board of Pharmacy.
Emswiller's innovation and dedication were recognized many times throughout his career. The most prestigious of the awards he received was the Remington Honor Medal in 1999, which is the profession of pharmacy's highest honor. Other awards include Virginia Pharmacist of the Year, 1981; the American Pharmaceutical Association's Daniel B. Smith Award, the highest honor given to a community pharmacist, 1983; Loudoun County Man of the Year, 1987; Outstanding Alumnus Award, MCV, Pharmacy Division, 1991; Virginia Pharmaceutical Association Outstanding Pharmacist Award, 1994; the Virginia Commonwealth University Alumni Star Award, 1999; and the American College of Apothecaries J. Leon Lascoff Memorial Award, 2000.
In 2000, Emswiller retired from his practice. He died on December 10, 2009. His wife Jewell, who also shared his passion and enthusiasm for collaborative, patient-centered pharmacy practice, endowed the Jewell and Carl Emswiller, Jr. Interprofessional Symposium, which was first held in 2013. The symposium is committed to educating health professional students and practitioners about providing meaningful patient care through innovative interprofessional practice.
The sources of information for this biography are Emswiller's bios and curriculum vitae found in this collection.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of correspondence, clippings, presentations, publications, photographs, speeches and other related materials. The items span Emswiller's 38 year career in pharmacy. There is a great deal of personal correspondence written to Emswiller by his colleagues and friends upon receipt of his many awards. The materials in the collection also provide insight into the evolvement of office-based, patient-centered pharmacy practices. This was a very innovative approach which spanned the transition from the traditional pharmacy of the early 20th century to the pharmacy model of the early 21st century.
The collection also includes some items of historical interest including Prohibition era prescriptions for whiskey and prescription preparation books from the late 19th to early 20th century.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically with the correspondence arranged chronologically. Efforts were made to retain the original order where possible.
Index Terms
Emswiller, Carl F. Jr., 1935-2009; Virginia Commonwealth University. School of Pharmacy; Pharmacy; Pharmacy -- Virginia -- history; Medicine -- Formulae, recipes, prescriptions
- Articles, 1962-1963, 1965, 1975, 1982-1983, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Articles from professional publications, some written by Emswiller.
- Articles - reprints, 1975, 1982-1984, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Audiovisual materials, undated, 1965 (Box 9)
  Includes 1965 film strip and 7-inch reel tape for "A New Horizon for Pharmacy," 7-inch reel tape, "Patient Compliance Program, NY Annual Meeting," 8mm film, "Kentucky School of Pharmacy," and one, 7-inch reel tape, unidentified.
- Awards- Daniel B. Smith Award, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Includes materials regarding the award and letters of congratulations.
- Awards - Loudon County Chamber of Commerce Man of the Year, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Awards - Outstanding Alumnus of the Year for the Pharmacy Division of the MCV Alumni Association, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Includes the plaque which is housed with oversized materials in box 8.
- Awards - Remington Honor Medal, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  This file contains materials and letters of congratulations regarding Emswiller's award. The framed medal is house with oversized materials in box 8.
- Awards - Virginia Pharmaceutical Association, Pharmacist of the Year, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Biography and curriculum vitae (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Certificates (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Clippings (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
  Contains newspaper clippings related to Emswiller's pharmacy and announcements about his various professional appointments and awards.
- Conference badges and pins (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1960s (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1970s (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
- Correspondence, 1990s (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 2000s (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Correspondence - Archambault, George F., 1986, 1992, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Correspondence - Haddon, Charles, Jr., 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Correspondence - Stieglitz, Oona, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Contains a complaint from a patient about services rendered at the pharmacy. Emswiller's response provides insight into the care he put into his practice and his wish to provide the best service possible.
- Edwards Drug Store ephemera, circa 1970 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  Emswiller purchased Edwards Drug Store, located on King Street in Leesburg, in 1968. He moved his practice to the Jackson Professional Building in 1974. Items include menus, bottle labels, stationary, and bags with the pharmacy name as well as a form letter to patients thanking them for choosing the pharmacy and explaining the use of the family record card.
- Emswiller Pharmacy - closing, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  Notices and letters related to the closing of Emswiller's pharmacy when he retired.
- Emswiller Pharmacy - ephemera (Box 3, Folder 8)
  Informational pamphlet, stationary, bags, and blank family record cards from the pharmacy when it was located at the Jackson Professional Building in Leesburg.
- Emswiller Pharmacy - inventory and sales analysis, 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  A summary of the value of the physical inventory of the pharmacy and the daily prescription sales analysis from October 1999 - March 2000.
- Emswiller Pharmacy - donation inventory, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  A deed of gift and detailed inventory of the contents of the Emswiller Pharmacy which was donated to the Hook's American Drugstore Museum in Indianapolis, Indiana
- Ephemera - miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Medical College of Virginia Clerkship Program, 1973, 1980, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Access to the student evaluations is restricted under FERPA.
  Includes information about the program and evaluations of the clerkship by students. Also contains some student evaluations.
- Medical College of Virginia, School of Pharmacy, 1959-1962 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  Contains materials related to Emswiller's acceptance into the School of Pharmacy, programs from the Kappa Psi pharmaceutical fraternity, commencement programs from his 1962 graduation, among other materials.
- Medical College of Virginia Reunion, 2001-2002 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Emswiller served as one of the reunion chairs for the 40th class reunion for Pharmacy; materials include a form letter to alumni, class list, program and two photographs of the attendees.
- Medial College of Virginia and Virginia Commonwealth University materials, 1980-2001 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  An assortment of materials related to MCV and VCU including faculty appointment letters to Emswiller, a letter from VCU President Eugene Trani congratulating him on his VPhA Outstanding Pharmacist Award, various event programs, and the Winter 2001 issue of The RX Exchange, which profiles Emswiller.
- Memorial Service Program, 2009-12-18 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  A program from Emswiller's memorial service.
- Pamphlets, Programs, and Publications, 1980-2001 (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
  Includes pamphlets and programs about various events and organizations and a few professional publications such as American Pharmacy and Virginia Pharmacist which include information about or by Emswiller and Eugene White.
- Petition against House Bill 206, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  Petition asking Virginia Governor Mills Godwin to veto the bill regarding price posting for prescriptions.
- Pharmaceutical Health Center Program, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  Information regarding the development and promotion of the center, include a blueprint design for an "ethical pharmacy."
- Pharmacy Ephemera - Prohibition Alcohol Prescriptions, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  Prescription forms issued by the US Treasury Department for the purpose of prescribing alcohol during prohibition. All the prescriptions were filled at Purcell and Littlejohn Pharmacy located on King Street in Leesburg, VA, which is the same street where Emswiller's first pharmacy was located.
- Pharmacy Ephemera - Prescription preparation books, circa late 19th to early 20th century (Box 4, Folder 9)
  Two bound volumes used to keep preparation instructions on various medicines and other compounds sold by pharmacies during that period. A page from a local newspaper (1866) was found inside one of the prescription books. It included a notice about Edwards Drug Store, which is the same one that Emswiller purchased in 1968.
- Photographs and slides, 1960s-2000s (Box 5, Folder 1-2, Box 8, Folder 1, Box 9)
  Includes photos from Emswiller's and White's pharmacies, from events such as award presentations, and various photos of Emswiller, his wife Jewell, and their friends.
- Presentations and speeches, undated, 1960s-2000s (Box 5, Folder 3-7)
- Presentations and speeches - Pharmacy Practice Institute, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Presentations and speeches - Merck lecture, 1983, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Presentations and speeches - Self care and the health professional, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Presentations and speeches - VCU School of Pharmacy commencement, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Presentations and speeches by colleagues (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Professional organizations - American College of Apothecaries (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Professional organizations - American Pharmaceutical Association, 1974-2009 (Box 6, Folder 7-8)
  Includes ephemera for the organization's 150th anniversary and the 50th anniversary of the American Institute of Pharmacy.
- Professional organizations - American Association of Colleges of Pharmacy, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Professional organizations - Florida Pharmacy Association conference, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Professional organizations - National Pharmaceutical Council (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Professional organizations - New Jersey Pharmaceutical Association, Drug Interaction Seminar, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Professional organizations - Virginia Pharmaceutical Association, 1973-1996 (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Project - Bush, "The Pharmacist Role in Disease Prevention and Health Promotion", 1981-1982 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  A project headed by Patricia Bush at Georgetown University to compile an edited edition of papers on the subject; Emswiller served as a reviewer.
- Retirement - autograph book, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Retirement - cards (Box 7, Folder 2-3)
- Scrapbook (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Virginia General Assembly Joint House Resolution No. 436, 1997
  Resolution commending Emswiller on his Outstanding Pharmacist award. Framed item.
- Virginia State Board of Pharmacy - exam results, 1922 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Virginia State Board of Pharmacy - appointment, 1991-1996 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  Materials related to Emswiller's appointment to the board including a letters from Governors Wilder and Allen
- Virginia State Board of Pharmacy - Patterson Drug Co. vs Kingery, 1969-1970 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  The case regarded prohibitions on advertising by pharmacists. Emswiller gave a deposition related to his experiences with the Family Record System. Materials include a copy of the decision, correspondence, and a newspaper clipping about the case.
- White, Eugene (Box 7, Folder 8-9)
  Materials include correspondence from White, items related to White's nomination for the Remington Honor Medal, (he was the 1978 recipient of this award) articles, and clippings.
- Writings (Box 7, Folder 10)